Preliminary Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by Adri de Ruijter
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates by Adri de Ruijter
1951-1966
BKP 72
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
This collection comprises bookplates and other works by the artist Adri de Ruijter (sometimes spelled Adri de Ruyter), who was active in Holland in the mid-20th century.
Ruijter, Adri de
Associated Materials
See also the Pearson-Lowenhaupt Collection of English and American Bookplates (Call # BKP 30) for additional Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt bookplates.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises bookplates and other works by the artist Adri de Ruijter (sometimes spelled Adri de Ruyter), who was active in Holland in the mid-20th century. In addition to bookplates, the collection also contains greeting cards, engraved portraits, and monograms, including many examples of the artist's personal designs. Series V of this collection contains materials related to a bookplate and metal stamp commission by de Ruijter for Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt, former curator of the Yale Bookplate Collection.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Bookplates. II. Greeting Cards. III. Other Works. IV. Personal Designs. V. Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt Commissions.
Bookplates; Bookplates; Greeting cards; Monograms; Lowenhaupt, Warren Hiram, 1891-1967; Ruijter, Adri de
- Bookplates, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains private bookplates arranged by the patron's last name.
  - Asselbergs – Wambeek, 1956 undated; 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Greeting Cards, Series II
  This series contains New Year's cards printed for both private individuals and businesses.
  - Hooijkaas – Swart, 1953-1958; 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    This folder contains three New Year's cards for printed for Schoonhovensche Zilverfabriek H. Hooijkaas, dated 1956-1958.
- Other Works, Series III
  This series contains other examples of de Ruijter's engraving.
  - Portraits, 1956 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Personal Designs, Series IV
  This series contains personal ex-libris, New Year's cards, and monogram designs by the artist for himself and his family.
  - Bookplates
    - R. – Ruijter, 1951 undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Greeting Cards
    - Adri de Ruyter – Fam. de Ruyter, 1951-1966; 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other Works
    - Monograms, 1960 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt Commissions, Series V
  This series contains materials related to a bookplate and metal stamp commission by de Ruijter for Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt, former curator of the Yale Bookplate Collection.
  - Correspondence, 1963; 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    This folder contains two letters written by de Ruijter and addressed to Lowenhaupt, which outline the details of both commissions.
  - Design drawings, 1963; 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    This folder contains three sample sketches for monogram ex-libris designs that de Ruijter sent to Lowenhaupt.
  - Plates, [1963]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This folder contains two engraved plates, one brass and one silver, which bear Lowenhaupt's monogram ex-libris based on design no. 1 sent by de Ruijter.
  - Bookplate, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This folder contains a print of Lowenhaupt's monogram ex-libris designed by de Ruijter.
  - Stamp and samples, [1963]; 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    This folder contains a metal stamp bearing a WHL monogram design by de Ruijter and two sample sheets stamped and signed by the artist.